It hasn't been that long since Anthropic
released skills to the world and it is
one of the most important advancements
in AI recently. And honestly, one of the
biggest reasons it is so important is
because of how beautifully simple it is
and that is the motto of anthropic. The
simpler the better. We see this looking
at Claude code as well. I mean, when you
get into how skills work and the idea of
progressive disclosure that we'll get
into, you can't help but thinking to
yourself, why in the world was skills
not commonplace ever since generative AI
was a thing? And people have been
building their own version of skills
before anthropic popularized it. It's
super easy to incorporate the idea of
skills and progressive disclosure into
any AI agent or tool that you want. And
that, my friend, is what I'm going to
show you how to do today. Because here's
the thing, and a lot of people don't
realize this. We are not limited to the
clawed ecosystem to take advantage of
skills. Anthropic does get a lot of
credit for popularizing the idea, and
we'll get into some of their best
practices for creating skills as well.
But this really is a universal concept.
It's all about strategizing how we can
allow the agent to discover context and
capabilities as it needs it to be more
flexible and context efficient as
opposed to something like an MCP server
or super long global rules where you're
just dumping a bunch of context into the
LLM right away and completely
overwhelming it. So, as much as I really
appreciate the anthropic ecosystem like
Claude Desktop and Claude Code, we don't
always want to be limited to these
platforms because a lot of the time you
want to build skills into your own
workflows or AI agents. You want to use
different large language models, maybe
even local AI. There's so many reasons
to incorporate skills into our own
systems and really build it out for
oursel. And that's what I'm going to
show you how to do. We're going to take
all of the concepts from Enthropics
version of skills and we're going to map
it into our own AI agent with the system
prompts and the tools we give it. And
it's beautifully simple, right? Simple
but powerful. And so this is only going
to take like 10 to 15 minutes. And then
you'll know after that exactly how to
build this kind of thing into your own
systems. And I've got a template for you
of course as well. All right. So there's
three things I want to cover with you in
the next 15 minutes. It's going to be
super valuepacked. So, first we need to
get into at a high level how skills work
and why they're so powerful, even if
you've used them before. Going over this
is going to be really valuable. Then
we'll get into the template that I have
for you. This is a GitHub repo that of
course I will have linked in the
description. And so, this is a
demonstration using Pyantic AI as my
agent framework, how we can build our
own idea of skills into any framework
that we want. And so I'll go over how
I'm building this with Pantic AI, but
the concept here is going to work no
matter what tool you end up using like
Langchain, Crew AI, Eggno, no framework
at all, literally anything that you
want. And then just as an opportunity
here to show you how far we can take our
custom agents, I also want to get into
evals and observability. So how can we
make sure our agent is really following
all the instructions and capabilities
that we give it? And so in our case
right here, that it's truly leveraging
the skills that we give. And so I'll get
into that at the end just as a bonus on
top of everything showing you how to
build skills for yourself. All right, so
now let's go over a really really quick
master class on skills, what they are,
why they are so important. So Anthropic
has this article that I'll link to in
the description, a really good guide,
and they cover best practices for
building skills that we'll talk about in
a little bit. And so the problem skills
are solving. We want to give our agent a
lot of different capabilities to
supercharge them, but we don't want to
overwhelm their context window. Agents
are very prone to being overwhelmed when
we give them a lot of information
through our tools, conversation history,
the system prompt, everything goes in
the window. And so other methods like
MCP servers, the problem there is we're
giving a ton of tools up front to the
agent even if it never needs to use them
in a specific conversation. That is bad.
And so with skills, the best way to
explain it is to go to a diagram here in
the article. And I also of course have
it blown up in another tab right here.
So the beautifully simple power of
skills is the idea of progressive
disclosure. Instead of giving all the
tools up front to our agent like MCP
servers, we are allowing our agent to
discover the capabilities over time as
it actually needs them. And so the only
thing we're giving to the agent right
away in the system prompt or you can
think of it like the global rules is the
description of the capability or the
skill. And so in this case as an example
we have a PDF processing skill. So we're
just telling the agent, hey you have
this capability if you need it. If the
user actually asks you to do something
with PDFs and then if the agent receives
that kind of request and it wants to
leverage the capability then it'll read
the skill.md. So the skill.md this is
the main file that drives any skill that
you'll see from anthropic and all the
ones that we'll go over with our custom
implementation here. And so this has the
full instructions for the capability.
Now it's starting to load in the
context. It's the second layer of
progressive disclosure, right? Like the
description is layer 1. This is layer
two. And then there are some other
documents oftentimes that the skill.md
will reference. This is the third layer
of progressive disclosure because we can
load in even more context. If you want
to get even more specific about
something with PDFs, for example, like
we have this extra set of instructions
for if we need to fill out some form,
some PDF form, right? Like not all the
time we're working with PDFs do we care
about this, but sometimes we do. So,
we're just discovering more and more
context over time as we actually need it
for the task at hand. And that saves the
LLM from being overwhelmed because if it
had all these documents and a dozen
other skills loaded all at once, it
would be tens of thousands of tokens
just to tell it right away all the
different capabilities that it has and
it probably only has to use one or two
of them in a single conversation. All
right, so with that explanation, I want
to now get into the template and exactly
how we are translating the ideas from
anthropic into our own agent
implementation. And again, I'm using
paidantic AI because it is my favorite
AI or agent framework. It has been for
over a year now. And so starting off, we
have the YAML front matter description,
which by the way, as far as best
practice goes, it's good to have this be
somewhere between 50 and 100 words. You
don't want to load in too much right
away, right? That defeats the purpose of
skill. So you want to be pretty short,
but at least descriptive enough so the
agent knows when it should leverage a
capability. So usually the skill is, you
know, something around 5% of the total
context of the skill. That's all you're
loading up front. Obviously, this is a
very very rough estimate. And so when we
think about our description here,
essentially every single skill that we
want our agent to have access to, we
need it to have the description and the
path to the skill in the system prompt.
And so we're going to be taking
advantage of what is called a dynamic
system prompt. We have our static
content, the main instructions for our
agent that doesn't really change. But
then also, we're going to collect the
descriptions from all YAML front
matters, all of our skill.mds, and we're
going to put that in our system prompt.
And I'll even get into the code just a
little bit with you and show you how
that works after we go through this
diagram here. And then we have our
skill.md, the main instructions for the
capability. And as far as best practices
go, usually you want this between 300
and 500 lines long. Now, obviously that
varies a ton depending on the
complexity. It could be a lot shorter as
well, but usually around 30% of the
total context for the skill if you have
a lot of reference files. Sometimes you
don't even need this third layer, by the
way, if the capability is simple enough.
But anyway, as far as how this
translates to our own system, our own
agent, we just need a simple tool.
Typically, this load skill tool is going
to take a path to the skill.md. And so,
the agent can invoke that. It can give
the path which should be in the system
prompt. And then we're just going to
take the skill.md and return that as the
tool response. And so now that is
included in the context for the agent
because every single time we call a
tool, whatever it returns is now in the
short-term memory for the agent. It is
that simple. So remember, system prompt
has the description and the path to the
skill. So it has all the context it
needs to know when it should leverage
the skill and then what parameter to
pass in as far as the path so it reads
that file. And then in the skill.md we
might also have references to our
reference files the third layer
progressive disclosure the scripts and
markdowns to read and leverage to take
the capabilities even further. And so I
have a second tool in my system for this
to read a reference document. And so you
just give as the parameters here the
skill and then the path to that
secondary file that you want to
leverage. And so this is where you have
unlimited depth. I mean you could have a
fourth layer progressive disclosure if
you want but that probably gets way too
complicated. So the rest of your skill
will just live in these files. And I
could combine these tools together. They
work very similarly because it's mainly
just to read a certain file. But in my
experience from the testing I've done,
it's helpful to the agent to know this
distinguishment. Like this is the main
instruction set for your capability. And
that's it. I told you it would be
simple. And I'll also show you the code
for the Pantic AI agent in a little bit
after a demo. All these different skills
that I have incorporated into the
template that I have for you. There's
quite a bit. Like you could extend this
to dozens and dozens and dozens and the
agent would still work well because
there's just that little bit of context
taken up front for each of the
capabilities. All right, so I have my
custom Pantic AI skills agent loaded up
here in the terminal. This is my
playground to test out all the different
skills that I have incorporated. And I
can just drop any skills that I want
into a skills folder just like you can
with Claude Code. And so this is using
the template that I'll link to in the
description. I've got instructions here
explaining how the skills work and a
quick start. Very, very easy to get this
up and running. Feel free to use this as
a resource. Give it to your AI coding
assistant if you want to incorporate
this all for yourself. I also use the
idea of a tool set in Pinantic AI. So,
you should be able to pull that out and
add skills into your own agent very
easily. Yeah, go ahead and take a look
at this. So, when I start the terminal,
it is reading all of the skill.md files
in my skill folder. It is loading all
these skills and so I can use any one of
them now. So for example, I can say help
me find a good dinner dish with chicken.
So it's going to use the recipe finder
and I have all the logs here on purpose
just so we have visibility into what's
going on. So you can see it really is
using the tool because we're loading the
skill recipe finder. And then from that
we have instructions to understand how
to leverage some kind of API that this
capability gives us. And so now it's
making that request to help get me get
some recipes that have chicken in it.
And take a look at that. I found lots of
delicious chicken options for you. And
wow. Okay, now I'm hungry. All right.
But anyway, now I can say like what is
the weather in uh Tokyo, Japan right
now. And so we'll see here that it's
going to leverage another skill. So
there we go. It's loading the weather
tool. And then it's going to make an API
request. And the only reason it knows
how to do this is because of the
instructions that we have here. And I
could even tell it to like uh load the
ref document for the weather skill
because there's the third layer
progressive disclosure if it needs more
information. I have this API reference.
So it can make more complicated
requests. And so that's a little bit
forced there, but I'm just trying to
show you an example of the third layer
of progressive disclosure as well. So
really, really cool. And the important
thing here is that based on our
conversation with the agent, we probably
only need to leverage one or two of
these at a time. I chose different
skills that are very different from each
other on purpose here to drive home the
point that like most of the time we
don't need all of this. So if we had an
MCP server for every single one of
these, we would just be overwhelming our
LLM for no reason. Okay. So now I want
to get into the code a little bit with
you to show how things are working under
the hood. And even if you're not super
technical, I'm going to keep this high
level. I'm just going to show you how
we're able to leverage this agent, how
you can use this for yourself. So, first
of all, in the readme here, I've got
instructions to set everything up. And
you can change this in your environment
variables. One of the things you can
specify is the directory where it
searches to load all the skills
dynamically into your agent. And so just
to keep things as similar to the
anthropic implementation as possible, I
have the skills directory just called
skills just like you have in cloud code
for example. And so there's a folder in
here for every single one of the skills
that we have. This looks just like the
anthropic skills where we have a
skill.md. This is our YAML front matter.
This is the description that's loaded
into the agent up front. I'll show you
how that works with the dynamic system
prompt. So the agent knows like, okay,
if I want to use a weather API, let me
read this entire skill. MD file so I can
use the API and I know how to do so. And
then the third layer of progressive
disclosure is optional, but for a lot of
these, we have the reference folder for
code review. We even have some Python
scripts that we can use. And so all of
these reference documents are called out
in the skill.md so the agent knows it
can go deeper to get those. And then for
some like the world clock, we literally
just have a skill.md because this is
just really like for converting time
zones. Obviously, we don't need that
much context for the agent to know how
to do that. And so it's just a pretty
simple skill.md only a couple of hundred
lines long. And so the way that this
works, I have my pideantic AI agent. I
have a lot of other content on my
channel covering Pyant AI. So I won't go
too much into the weeds here, but we
have our agent definition, which by the
way, this agent you can use Open Router,
O Lama, or OpenAI, easy to extend it for
others as well. So again, not stuck to
the clawed ecosystem. And what we're
doing here is we are creating a dynamic
system prompt. And so when we first
define the agent, we're not setting the
system prompt at all because we're going
to do it right here. And so in pineanti
the way the way that you do this is you
reference your agent dotsystem prompt.
This is our Python decorator. Now the
function below this is where we get to
define the system prompt for our agent.
So we can inject things at runtime
because what we're doing with this line
of code right here is we're calling a
function that I'm not going to get into
the weeds of that is going to search
this skills directory. It's going to
find every single skill.md take the YAML
front matter. It's going to extract that
from the skill.m MD and then put it into
the system prompt. And so we have all of
the descriptions of the skills and their
paths as well as our primary system
prompt. So we still have our base
instructions that don't change. In fact,
a lot of my instructions here is just
telling the agent how to use skills. So
it's very important. Large language
models by themselves do not understand
how to leverage these capabilities. What
Claude did and what we have to do oursel
is be very descriptive here. Like here's
what skills are. Here's the metadata so
you know the ones that are available to
you. And then here is step by step how
you leverage a skill when the
description is screaming out to you that
you want to use that capability. So all
the prompting that I went over here is
the first layer of progressive
disclosure. The dynamic system prompt is
how we are letting the agent know about
everything upfront. And so then we get
into our tool set. And so I'm giving a
single tool set to my Pantic AI agent
that has everything it needs to work
with the skills to basically read
everything we have in the skills
directory. And so going to that
definition here, there are three tools
that we are giving. So we have the load
skill and read reference. And then one
other tool that I have here just to make
it easier for the agent is to list the
reference documents just in case the
skill.md doesn't reference it directly
at that at least then our agent is still
able to find it. So we're just trying to
make it as easy as possible to discover
everything. That's the whole point of
skills is discovering the capabilities
that it has access to. And so for
example, to load a skill, we just have
to give the name of the skill. That's
one of the things that's included in the
system prompt. And so what we do here is
we have our skill path that's set in our
environment variable and then we have
the name and then we're looking for the
skill.md there. And so we're loading all
of that and then we're returning the
content of the skill.md. That's how
we're including it now in the context
window for the agent going forward. And
it's very similar for when we're reading
one of our reference documents as well.
The code is actually almost identical,
but there are some differences there to
make sure that we're reading a reference
document specific to the skill. some
protections that I have in place for the
agent. And so, yeah, that's pretty much
the agent as a whole. Like, that's
that's how it works. It's super simple
in the end. And also, because I have
this as a Pantic AI tool set, you can
take this tool set, like you could copy
this file and then just a couple of
these other ones here, and you could
bring this into your own Pantic AI agent
in just a couple of minutes. And your AI
coding assistant could help you do this
so incredibly fast. So, please use this
as a resource for yourself. just give it
this repository and say like, "Hey, I
have all these skills." You can put like
literally any skill that you want in
this folder right here and then the next
time you interact with the agent, it'll
have those capabilities automatically.
So, very dynamic system that I built for
you. Really good starting point for any
kind of system you want to create. Now,
one other really important thing to
cover here is how you can build your own
skills. And so, this guide that I have
linked in the description is a really
good starting point. Another quick tip
that I have for you, super useful. If
you go in Claw Desktop, you can use it
to help you build your skills that you
can then bring into the skill directory
for your custom agent. So, you just go
to file settings and then capabilities.
You scroll all the way down to skills,
go to example skills, and you can toggle
on the skill creator. So, this is really
meta, but this is a skill to help you
build more skills. So when Claude uses
this, it's going to pull in all the
instructions and best practices for
creating skills and guide you through
that process. You can go here and say
like, "Hey, help me build a skill for
LinkedIn posting or help me build a
skill to generate powerpoints or to
create standard operating procedures,
like whatever you need." And it'll walk
you through creating that. And then
it'll create a skill.md and then
potentially some of those reference
documents and you can take that and just
put it in a new folder here in the
skills directory. It is that easy to
build your own skills and the sky's is
the limit for the capabilities that you
can create. All right, so at this point
we now know the importance of skills and
how to build them into any agent that we
want. But the big question we have here
is reliability. When we take these
capabilities and you could have dozens
of skills, you give them to your agent.
How do you know that the agent is always
going to leverage them when you want it
to? Like you might have a skill for
creating X posts, but you ask it to help
you with content creation and it doesn't
pull that skill because it doesn't know
that content creation should mean that
it should pull the X skill, right? Like
you want to test for those things, but
when you have dozens of different
skills, it's really annoying to interact
with the agent and send in a question
and make sure it's using each one of
them properly every single time you make
changes to your agent. So that is where
eval comes in. we can create an
automated way to define questions and
the expected tool calls or in this case
the expected skills that it leverages.
And so I'll cover what that looks like
with you and then also get into
observability. So when our agent is
running in production using these
different skills, we can look at how
real users are interacting with our
agent and making sure the agent is
responding appropriately. And I'm pretty
excited to get into this for the last
part of the video here. I'm going to be
pretty brief, but this is something I
don't get to cover enough on my channel.
Evals and observability are things that
are super important, but I don't get to
make content on it on my channel very
much. So, luckily for us, Pideantic AI
has a very robust evaluation framework
built right in. And so, essentially what
we can do is create these YAML files
where we define all of our test cases.
And so, for example, I'm going to send
in the question, what's [snorts] the
weather in New York right now? And then
I have an evaluator to make sure that
the weather skill was loaded. So we can
also create our custom evaluators. I
don't want to get into the code too much
right now. You can read up on this in
the documentation. Use this as an
example for your AI coding assistant.
But I have this custom evaluator to make
sure that the right skills are loaded
based on the questions that I send in.
So now instead of me having to go into
the agent and ask it each of these
things to make sure it's using the
different skills like the code review
skill and the research assistant skill,
now I can just run this single script.
So I can call this Python script right
here to run my evaluators. It loads in
my golden data set as I call it. Goes
through the questions one at a time. So,
I am paying for the LLM credits, but
these are really cheap, really fast,
just a smoke test to make sure that all
the different skills that I've added to
my folder are actually being used
properly by my agent. If it's not, then
it means that maybe there's an issue in
my loading capability or just my system
prompt needs to be better or the skill
descriptions need to be better. Like,
there's definitely different things that
need to be adjusted if the agent isn't
working as you expect it to. And so eval
are very important to run every single
time you change the system prompt for
your agent or even just the skills that
you're giving it access to. So I also
have instructions in the readme for how
to run the evals. And you can feel free
to poke around in the code for this as
well if you want to see how to set this
up for your own Pantic AI agents. But
you want to do this for pretty much any
agent you're deploying to production.
Evals are so important and skills is
just a good example because there's just
so many different capabilities that we
want to test for here. So logs are
pretty verbose. Uh but I'm just using
Haiku for all the tests here. So it's
really nice and fast. But at the bottom
here, 25 out of 25 cases have passed.
And so I've sent in a lot of different
requests to make sure the agent properly
understands all of the skills that I've
given it. So it's good to do this
instead of having to do a bunch of
manual testing myself after every single
time I adjust my agent. So, I'll also
link to this page for padantic evals in
the description if you want to dive into
this and really take your agent
seriously before deploying them to
production. And the other thing I want
to talk about is observability with
logfire because eval are great when you
want to test your agent locally, but how
about when users are actually using your
agent in production, but you want to be
able to peer into the traces as they're
called to see the decisions your agent
is making when people are using it out
in the wild. And so, that's why we need
a tool like Logfire. So it's created by
the Pantic team. They also made Pyantic
AI. So it's just a fantastic integration
to have here. And it's really easy to
set it up. And so there's just a minimal
amount of code that I have to have in my
agent definition file. So the logfire
token is one of the environment
variables. I explained that in the
readme. And then we can configure
logfire. So it's going to instrument all
the podantic agents as in every time we
invoke a tool interact with the LLM.
It's going to send all of that as
telemetry data. So we can track this
running it locally like you're seeing
right here, but then also in production.
And so yeah, I'm also going to have a
link to Logfire. I just wanted to
mention this quick like this is so
important being able to see our usage
like token usage and cost in production.
Looking into the different traces, like
if a user reports a problem, we can go
in here and see like, okay, where did
the agent mess up? Like is it something
wrong with their system? Did it just use
a tool incorrectly like a bad parameter?
We can look at all the parameters, all
the tool calls that it made. So we can
see the decisions even when we're not
running the agent locally. It's very
very important to have evals and
observability when you want to take your
agent seriously and paid with logfire
and pantic AI just makes it so easy. So
there you go. That is your guide for
building skills into any AI agent that
you want. And you even got a bit of a
bonus with evals and observability
because it is important to make sure
we're constantly checking our agent
making sure that it's leveraging our
tools properly. Because with skills, we
can give our agents dozens and dozens of
capabilities like I've shown you here.
So, if you appreciate this video and
you're looking forward to more things on
building AI agents, I would really
appreciate a like and a subscribe. And
with that, I will see you in the next